我们是仅存的一家了
We were the last ones around.
曾经有很多邻居
There used to be neighbors.
高茨一家  被猛犸象踩扁了
The Gorts, smashed by a mammoth.
霍克一家  被沙蛇吞了
The Horks, swallowed by a sand snake.
他不但强壮  而且遵守规则
He was strong, and he followed the rules,
新鲜事物都很危险  好奇心也很危险
Anything new is bad. Curiosity is bad.
总而言之  有趣的事情都危险
Basically, anything fun is bad.
欢迎来到我的世界
Welcome to my world.
你应该等我信号的  小伊
You're supposed to wait for my signal, Eep.
小伊
Eep.
我就回洞里  你就可以发信号了
I'll go back in, and you can give the signal.
没事了  桑克  出来吧
Never mind, Thunk. Just come out.
可如果你不发信号  我怎么知道你是我老爸？
But if you don't give me the signal, how do I know you're my dad?
信号不是为了验明我的正身
The signal isn't so you know it's me.
是为了证明我还没被野兽吃掉
It's so you know I wasn't eaten by an animal.
那为何信号是野兽叫啊？
Then why is the signal an animal noise?
我还在等信号
I'm still waiting for the signal.
谢谢啦
Thanks.
小伊  启动刹车！
Eep, put on the brakes!
小伊！
Eep!
干得好  老爸
Good one, Dad.
给你  桑克  尽情喝吧
Here you go, Thunk. Drink up.
黑暗意味着死亡！  都明白吧
Darkness brings death! We know this.
我可不想被洗掉保护皮
I don't want to lose my protective layer.
妈妈  你身上都长蚂蚁了
Mom, you've got ants.
看看 ？ 仙蒂都不闹
See? Sandy doesn't fuss.
请你明天一定要回来
Please come back tomorrow.
她怎么会不喜欢洞穴？  多温馨啊
How can she not like the cave? It's so cozy.
太黑了点  是吧？
It is a little dark, right?
小伊
Eep!
快来  我要关门了
Come on, I gotta close the cave.
小伊！
Eep!
恐惧让我们生存  小伊
Fear keeps us alive, Eep.
这一切有何意义呢？
What's the point of all this?
没人说生存是件趣事
No one said survival is fun.
一切都了无生趣
Nothing is fun.
好的  能借用一下吗？  多谢
Okay. Can I borrow that? Thank you.
我明白  老爸  我永远不会去尝鲜
I get it, Dad. I will never do anything new or different.
哇  你可真是强壮
Wow, you're really strong.
加油  加油
Come on, come on
我同意  虎妞  我们必须马上离开
I concur. Tiger girl, we need to leave immediately.
我都不认识你
I don't even know you.
首先  大地会颤抖  然后裂开
First, the ground is gonna shake. Then it breaks open.
跟我来吧
Come with me.
如果你能活下来  呼叫我
If you survive, call me.
谢谢
Thank you.
没有  我自己出来的
Nothing. I left on my own.
你从不让我解释
You never let me talk.
你被关禁闭了
You're grounded.
阿瓜！  怎么回事？
Grug! What happened?
我找到了一样新东西
I found something new.
你们有毛病吗？
What is wrong with you?
什么？
What?
你不能关我一辈子！
You can't keep me inside forever!
小心！
Look out!
停！
Stop!
不
No.
你们真该来看看
You really need to see this.
哪儿都不许去
No one is going anywhere.
那男孩还说了什么？
What else did that boy say?
六个
Six.
有一点可以确定  我们回不去了
One thing's for sure, we can't go back the way we came.
我们不能像这样暴露在外面
We can't be out in the open like this.
我们要找个洞穴
We need a cave.
踩着我的脚印走
Now step where I step.
好的  保持安静
Okay. Stay quiet.
希望还没有大家伙注意到我们
Hopefully nothing big knows we're here yet.
等等！  好了
Wait! Okay.
等等！
Wait!
好了  等等
Okay. Wait.
等等
Wait.
好的  爸爸  拿下它们
All right, Dad, go get them.
爸爸  我知道了
Dad, I got this.
六个
Six.
他怕黑！
He's scared of the dark!
小伊！
Eep!
好的  闭上眼
All right. Close your eyes.
我来取他们性命
I'm going to have to take their lives.
不  没用的  他们是我的家人
No, it won't help. They're my family.
什么
What?
我们现在就坐在这儿等太阳出来
Now we'll all sit here and wait for the sun to come back.
明天我们去找一个新的洞穴
tomorrow we'll find a new cave
鬼知道他从哪冒出来的
Goodness knows where he's been.
爸爸  仙蒂在伤害火！
Dad, Sandy's hurting fire!
没错  但我不会让他得逞的
Yeah. But I won't let him.
等一下  儿子  回来！
Hold on, son, come back!
它停不下来  别碰我！
It won't stop. Stop touching me!
滚开！
Get out!
尽情吃吧  宝宝们！
Eat up, babies!
我赢了
I win!
跟魔术一样！
Looks like magic!
来吧  继续吃！
Come on, keep eating!
已经发生了  它毁了我们的洞穴
That already happened. It destroyed our cave.
不  这只是末日的前兆
No. That was just the beginning of the end.
真正的末日还在后头
The end of the end is still coming.
小伊  把他放下
Eep. Drop it.
我们不能让他跑了！
We can't let him go!
要是日落前没找到洞穴怎么办？
What if we don't find a cave before sunset?
要是得找上好几天怎么办？
What if it takes a few days?
要是那群鸟又来了怎么办？
What if the birds come back?
我们需要他的火  笨蛋！
We need his fire, dummy!
好吧  你就待到我们找到洞穴为止
Fine. You're staying with us until we find a cave.
你们想留下就留下  但是放我走
Stay here if you want, but let me go.
我还有梦想  有使命
I've got a dream, a mission,
山上也有洞穴
There are caves on that Mountain.
你去过了？
Have you been there?
那是座山
It's a mountain.
山上很安全  山上有洞穴
Mountains are safe. Mountains have caves.
妈妈  你听见没？
Mom, did you hear that?
我可以有自己的树枝了！
I can get my own stick!
那玩意真奇怪
That thing is weird.
不不不  没事  仙蒂
No. No. No. It's okay, Sandy.
我们可从来没走过这么远
We've never really walked that far.
我的脚可受不了
I don't think my feet can do that.
我可活不到走到的那一天
I'll never live long enough to get there.
那我们走吧
Let's do it.
来吧  你们想一想
come on, just think.
我们全家人一起
Our whole family, packed together
一家人的感情会更好
We'll become closer as a family.
是不是很有趣？  我们第一次一起旅行
Isn't this fun? We're taking our first trip together.
别推我  不然我拔掉你舌头
Stop shoving, or I will pull out your tongue!
仙蒂  快把那东西吐出来
Sandy, take that out of your mouth.
我不要做个饿死鬼
I'm not dying on an empty stomach.
阿瓜  我们都很累了
Grug, we're all pretty tired.
我们管那种东西叫小孩
We call those children.
人不应该养宠物
No man should have a pet.
不是它  是它！
Not that. That!
食物能解决任何问题
Food fixes everything.
好了  进入狩猎状态
All right, show me your hunting face.
不是你！  你还在禁闭中
Not you! You're still grounded.
来吧  桑克
Come on, Thunk.
我的脚好痛
My feet hurt.
我还没准备好
I wasn't ready.
坚持住  桑克  我来了
Hang on, Thunk. I'm coming.
你身上没肉
You're too skinny.
稳住她  用石头
Hold her still. Use a rock.
你一个人过多久了？
How long have you been alone?
那我们要做什么？
So what do we do?
你的演技如何？
How's your acting?
你很擅长这个啊
You're good at this.
不对  抱歉  不是  就这样
No, Sorry. No. Okay.
不好意思
Excuse me.
她好厉害
She's awesome.
小伊！
Eep!
老爸  别！
Dad, no!
看样子是不会剩了
Looks like we won't have any leftovers.
阿瓜  来讲个故事吧？
Grug, how about a story?
很久以前  有只小老虎
Once upon a time, there was a little tiger
她前脚刚走  她家的山洞就被毁了
And no sooner than she did, her cave was destroyed
我的故事是不会就这样潦草结束的
My stories never end like that.
太好了  一晚上俩故事
Yes! Two stories in one night!
好吧  但没有阿瓜的那么精彩
Okay, but it won't be as good as Grug's.
很久以前  有只美丽的老虎
Once upon a time, there was a beautiful tiger.
她和家人住在一个山洞里
She lived in a cave with the rest of her family.
她飞去了哪里？
Where did she fly?
在那里  天空中的星星多得数不清
A place with more suns in the sky than you can count.
那会很明亮啊
It would be so bright.
那里不像今天亦或昨天
A place not like today, or yesterday.
那里的一切都更美好
A place where things are better.
明天又不是个地方
Tomorrow isn't a place.
那就是我要去的地方
That's where I'm going.
行了  该去睡觉了
Well, we are going to shut our eyes and sleep.
有我看着呢  没事
I was watching. We were fine.
那只老虎是怎么飞的？
How did the tiger fly?
那样我才有激情
I'm funny that way.
看我的吧
Leave this to me.
桑克  你脸上有只蜘蛛
Thunk, you have a spider on your face.
他跑掉了！
He's loose!
别去踩那些奇怪的尖石头！
Do not step on those weird, pointy rocks!
你是说这些石头吗？
You mean these rocks?
千万不要踩  ！
Do not step on these rocks!
那好
Okay.
现在  让我们朝那座山迈进吧
Now let's get to that Mountain.
笑话是什么
What's a joke?
你的方法不安全
Your way isn't safe.
保护你们的安全是我的责任
It's my job to keep you safe.
这里还是我说了算
I'm still in charge,
老爸  我有点害怕
Dad, I'm freaking out a little bit.
告诉我该怎么做
Just tell me what to do.
所有人都往前走  我们会走出去的
Everybody, keep moving forward and we'll get out.
是的  好吧
Yeah. Okay.
记住  千万不要害怕
Remember, never not be afraid.
我要晕过去了
I'm gonna pass out.
再给我一朵
Give me another one.
你掉东西了
You dropped these.
跟我走
Come with me.
阿瓜?
Grug?
我去接他
I'll go get him.
你能做动作吗?
Can you do tricks?
翻身
Roll over.
我们喂对方吃浆果  一起跳舞
We fed each other berries. We danced.
然后我爸用石头把他捶成肉泥
Then my father smashed him with a rock,
阿瓜  他们没事
Grug, they're okay.
有盖伊在呢
Guy's with them.
这些天是他们生命中最多彩的日子
they had the best day in their lives.
我带你们看样东西
I wanna show you something.
数都数不清的太阳
More suns in the sky than you can count.
我要跟盖伊一起走
I'm going with Guy.
跟我们一起走吧
Come with us.
我不能扔下阿瓜
I can't go without Grug.
阿瓜根本不知道怎么保护我们
Grug has no idea how to protect us.
绘画已经过时了
Painting is a thing of the past.
你哪来的这些好主意?
Where do you get these great ideas?
你懂的  双赢
you know, win-win.
我们要乘着太阳和盖伊一起去明天
We're gonna jump on the sun and ride it to Tomorrow with Guy.
还记得今早你什么样吗?
Remember how you were this morning?
你变了  记得吗?
You changed, remember?
我知道
I know.
对不起
Sorry.
当时我还很小
I was little when it happened.
你追求光明  我女儿很像你
You followed the light. My daughter is a lot like you.
不  他像你
No. She's like you.
她爱你  却总是忘记说出口
She loves you but always forgets to say it,
也许因为我总是忙着保护他们
I guess I was just busy keeping them all alive.
来吧  你行的
Come on, you can do it.
抓紧了!
Hold on!
我们没事!
We're okay!
我们很好
We're okay.
带我们去明天吧
Take us to Tomorrow.
不要黑暗  不再躲藏
No more dark. No more hiding.
这是个机会
It's a chance.
他成功了!
He made it!
他成功了
He made it.
桑克  该你了
Thunk. Your turn.
你真棒
You did good.
老爸
Daddy.
等下  你今天让我刮目相看  傻孩子
Wait! You surprised me today. Lunkhead.
我想弥补一切  却没有时间了
I need to fix everything, and I don't have time.
我会弥补的
I can fix it.
感觉真好
This works good.
我爱你
I love you.
我...
I...
老爸
Dad,
拿着
Hold this.
我...有...
I... have...
跑!
Run!
这里不安全
It's not safe here.
我去和她说吧
I'll tell her.
小伊  要是你老爸在  他会让你...
Eep, if your dad were here, he would tell you to...
七
seven.
你们快来看啊
You really need to see this.
我们去那里吧
We should go there.
这就是我  我是小伊
This is me. My name is Eep.
这是我们一家  克鲁德一家
this is my family, the Croods.
我们不再是原始人了
we're not exactly cavemen anymore.
放出宝宝!
Release the baby!